Maitraye Das

https://maitraye.github.io/ ma.das@northeastern.edu, maitraye@uw.edu

Research Summary

My research interest sits broadly at the intersection of Human-Computer Interaction (HCI), Computer-Supported Cooperative Work (CSCW), and Accessible Computing, with a focus on enhancing accessibility in collaboration, creativity, and learning. Methodologically, I take a community-centered research approach that involves in-depth qualitative studies (e.g., contextual interviews, observations, long-term fieldwork) followed by the iterative design, development, and evaluation of new systems. As a researcher and educator, my broader goal is to cultivate a culture of access and inclusion in computing and contribute towards reducing equity gaps in education, employment, and creative work.

Appointments

Northeastern University, Boston, MA, USA

Assistant Professor

Staring in Jan 2024

Khoury College of Computer Sciences

Department of Art + Design, College of Arts, Media and Design (CAMD)

• Research Fellow | Khoury College of Computer Sciences

Sep – Dec 2023

Visiting Assistant Professor | Khoury College of Computer Sciences

Oct 2022 - Aug 2023

University of Washington, Seattle, WA, USA

Postdoctoral Research Fellow

Sep 2022 – Aug 2023

Center for Research and Education on Accessible Technology and Experiences (CREATE) Paul G. Allen School of Computer Science and Engineering

Education

PhD in Technology and Social Behavior

2022

(Dual degree in Computer Science & Communication)

Northwestern University, Evanston, IL, USA

Dissertation: Designing for Accessible Collaborative Content Creation in Ability-Diverse Teams Committee: Darren Gergle (chair), Anne Marie Piper (co-chair), Marcelo Worsley, and Cynthia Bennett

MS in Technology and Social Behavior

2021

Northwestern University, Evanston, IL, USA

BS in Computer Science and Engineering (CSE) with Honors & Magna cum laude

2015

Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology (BUET)

Thesis: Protecting Genomic Privacy in Medical Tests using Distributed Storage Advisor: Tanzima Hashem

Peer-Reviewed Publications

[Top-tier venues in Human-Computer Interaction include extensively peer-reviewed conferences such as CHI and CSCW. These highly selective conferences are intended for archival papers and comparable to journals in visibility, selectively, and impact. Directly mentored students are marked with an asterisk (*).]

- P12. **Maitraye Das**, Darren Gergle, Anne Marie Piper. 2023. Simphony: Enhancing Accessible Pattern Design Practices among Blind Weavers. In *Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '23)*. [acceptance rate: 28.39%]
- P11. **Maitraye Das**, *Thomas McHugh, Anne Marie Piper, and Darren Gergle. 2022. Co11ab: Augmenting Accessibility in Synchronous Collaborative Writing for People with Vision Impairments. In *Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '22)*. [first-round acceptance rate: 12.5%]
- P10. **Maitraye Das,** Anne Marie Piper, and Darren Gergle. 2022. Design and Evaluation of Accessible Collaborative Writing Techniques for People with Vision Impairments. In *ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction (TOCHI)*, Vol. 29, 2, Article 9 (April 2022). [Impact Factor: 4.11]
- P9. Maitraye Das, John Tang, Kathryn E. Ringland, and Anne Marie Piper. 2021. Towards Accessible Remote Work: Understanding Work-from-Home Practices of Neurodivergent Professionals. In Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction, Vol. 5, CSCW1, Article 183.

 [Impact Factor: 4.57]

Best Paper Award (top 1% of submissions)

Recognition for Contribution to Diversity & Inclusion

QP8. Kelly Mack, **Maitraye Das**, Dhruv Jain, Danielle Bragg, John Tang, Andrew Begel, Erin Beneteau, Josh Urban Davis, Abraham Glasser, Joon Sung Park, and Venkatesh Potluri. 2021. Mixed Abilities and Varied Experiences: A Group Autoethnography of a Virtual Summer Internship. In *Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Computers and Accessibility (ASSETS '21)*. [acceptance rate: 29%]

Best Paper Nomination

Invited article in Communications of the ACM Research Highlights

- P7. Katya Borgos-Rodriguez, **Maitraye Das**, and Anne Marie Piper. 2021. Melodie: A Design Inquiry into Accessible Crafting through Audio-Enhanced Weaving. In *ACM Transactions on Accessible Computing (TACCESS)*, Vol. 14, 1, Article 5 (March 2021). [Impact Factor: 3.20]
- Maitraye Das, Katya Borgos-Rodriguez, and Anne Marie Piper. 2020. Weaving by Touch: A Case Analysis of Accessible Making. In *Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '20)*. [acceptance rate: 24.3%]
 Best Paper Honorable Mention (Top 5% of submissions).
- Maitraye Das, Darren Gergle, and Anne Marie Piper. 2019. "It doesn't win you friends":
 Understanding Accessibility in Collaborative Writing for People with Vision Impairments. In
 Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction, Vol. 3, CSCW, Article 191.
 [Impact Factor: 4.57]

Best Paper Honorable Mention (Top 5% of submissions)

- P4. **Maitraye Das,** Brent Hecht, and Darren Gergle. 2019. The Gendered Geography of Contributions to OpenStreetMap: Complexities in Self-Focus Bias. In *Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '19)*, Paper 563. [acceptance rate: 23.8%]
- P3. *Nusrat Jahan Mazumder, **Maitraye Das,** Tanzima Hashem, Sharmin Afrose, and *Khandaker Ashrafi Akbar. 2019. Towards Privacy-preserving Authenticated Disease Risk Queries. In *Journal of Information Processing*, Vol. 27 (September 2019).
- P2. Moushumi Sharmin, Monsur Hossain, Abir Saha, **Maitraye Das,** Margot Maxwell, and Shameem Ahmed. 2018. From Research to Practice: Informing the Design of Autism Support Smart

- Technology. In *Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '18)*, Paper 102. [acceptance rate: 25%]
- ₱ P1. Maitraye Das, *Nusrat Jahan Mazumder, Sharmin Afrose, *Khandaker Ashrafi Akbar, and Tanzima Hashem. 2018. A Novel Secret Sharing Approach for Privacy-Preserving Authenticated Disease Risk Queries in Genomic Databases. In Proceedings of the 42nd IEEE International Conference on Computers, Software, and Applications (COMPSAC '18). [acceptance rate: 24%]
 Best Paper Award

Book Chapter

B1. **Maitraye Das,** Katya Borgos-Rodriguez, and Anne Marie Piper. In Press. A Case Study of Skilled Craftwork among Blind Fiber Artists. In Elizabeth Guffey ed. *After Universal Design: The Disability Design Revolution*. Bloomsbury.

Doctoral Consortium

D1. **Maitraye Das.** 2020. Designing for Collaborative Content Creation for People with Vision Impairments. In the *Conference Companion Publication on Computer Supported Cooperative Work & Social Computing (CSCW '20)*.

Workshop Co-organized

W1. Maryam Bandukda, Giulia Barbareschi, Aneesha Singh, Dhruv Jain, **Maitraye Das,** Tamanna Motahar, Jason Wiese, Lynn Cockburn, Amit Prakash, David Frohlich, Catherine Holloway. 2022. A Workshop on Disability Inclusive Remote Co-Design. In *Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Computers and Accessibility (ASSETS '22)*.

Short Papers, Posters, and Presentations

- S15. Maitraye Das. 2021. Augmenting Ability-Diverse Collaboration. In MIT EECS Rising Stars Workshop.
- S14. **Maitraye Das.** 2021. Designing for Accessible Collaborative Content Creation for People with Vision Impairments. In *Human-Computer Interaction Consortium (HCIC '21)*.
- S13. **Maitraye Das.** 2021. Rethinking Power and Politics in Care Work within Ability-Diverse Maker Communities. In the *Workshop on The Future of Care Work at the ACM Conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work & Social Computing (CSCW '21).*
- S12. **Maitraye Das,** Katya Borgos-Rodriguez, and Anne Marie Piper. 2020. Rethinking Power and Politics in Accessible Making. In the *Workshop on Investigating the Role of Critical Disability Studies in HCI at the ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '20).*
- S11. **Maitraye Das.** 2019. Who Can See What: Privacy and Audience Management for People with Vision Impairments on Social Media. In the *Workshop on Addressing the Accessibility of Social Media at the ACM Conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work & Social Computing (CSC W'19).*
- S10. **Maitraye Das.** 2019. Designing for Collaborative Content Creation for People with Vision Impairments. *Microsoft Research PhD Fellowship Finalist Presentation*, Redmond, WA, USA.
- S9. **Maitraye Das.** 2018. Understanding Collaborative Writing Practices of People with Visual Impairments. In the *ACM International Conference on Pervasive and Ubiquitous Computing (UbiComp '18)*.

- S8. **Maitraye Das.** 2018. Towards Understanding the Effects of Social Networking on Postpartum Depression in Women. *Grace Hopper Celebration (GHC)*, USA.
- S7. Abir Saha and **Maitraye Das.** 2017. Impact of Social Networking on Post-Partum Depression in Women: An Analysis in the Context of Bangladesh. In *Proceedings of the 20th IEEE International Conference on Computer and Information Technology (ICCIT '17)*.
- S6. **Maitraye Das** and Abir Saha. 2017. An Automated Speech-Language Therapy Tool with Interactive Virtual Agent and Peer-to-Peer Feedback. In *Proceedings of the 4th International Conference on Advances in Electrical Engineering (ICAEE '17)*.
- S5. *Fatema Khan and **Maitraye Das**. 2016. Safe Teens: Supporting Parental Monitoring of Children's Internet Activities. In *the ACM Student Research Competition at the Grace Hopper Celebration (GHC)*, USA.
- S4. *Fatema Khan, **Maitraye Das**, and *Ahiya Ahammed. 2016. PurpleAid: An mHealth Platform to Combat Health Hazards of Women. In *Proceedings of the 2016 International Conference on Medical Engineering, Health Informatics and Technology (MediTec '16)*.
- S3. **Maitraye Das,** Sunandita Sarker, and Syeda Lammim Ahad. 2016. A Novel Health Support System with Biometric Data Acquisition Device. In *Proceedings of the 19th International Conference on Computer and Information Technology (ICCIT'16)*.
- S2. **Maitraye Das,** Sharmin Afrose, and Tanzima Hashem. 2015. Protecting Genomic Privacy in Medical Tests using Distributed Storage. *Grace Hopper Celebration of Women in Computing (GHC)*, USA.
- ¶ S1. Maitraye Das, Sunandita Sarker, and Shahina Ferdous. 2014. SpeechAid: A Self-treatment System for Individuals with Speech Disorder. Grace Hopper Celebration India (GHCI).

 Best Technical Poster Award

Magazine Article

M1. Maria Hamdani, Najma Farrukh Hamdani, **Maitraye Das.** Under Review. How to Enhance Productivity of Your Employees with ADHD in the Virtual Workplace. In *MIT Sloan Management Review*.

Awards and Honors

•	Communications of the ACM Research Highlights (CACM-RH) [P8] From ACM's website: "With a readership of over 100,000 from over 100 countries, publication is CACM-RH provides unmatched visibility and is regarded as a significant honor."	2022 n
•	Donald H. and Carolyn E. Ecroyd Fellowship Department of Communication Studies, Northwestern University	2022
•	Rising Star in Electrical Engineering and Computer Science (EECS) Massachusetts Institute of Technology	2021
•	Best Paper Award [P9] ACM Conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work & Social Computing (CSCW)	2021
•	Recognition for Contribution to Diversity & Inclusion [P9] ACM Conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW)	2021
•	Best Paper Nomination [P8] ACM Conference of Computers and Accessibility (ASSETS)	2021

•	PhD Student Research Award Dept. of Computer Science, Northwestern University	2021		
•	Best Paper Honorable Mention Award [P6] ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI)	2020		
•	Finalist (among top 20 students) Microsoft Research PhD Fellowship	2020		
•	Best Paper Honorable Mention Award [P5] ACM Conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CS	2019 SCW)		
•	Special Recognition for Outstanding Review ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI), 5 times ACM Conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work (CSCW), 2 times ACM Conference on Designing Interactive Systems (DIS)	2021–2023 2021, 2019 2022		
•	Best Paper Award [P1] IEEE International Conference on Computers, Software, and Applications (COMPSAC)	2018		
•	Student Scholarship Grace Hopper Celebration USA	2018		
•	Best Undergraduate Thesis Award Dept. of CSE, Bangladesh U of Engg. & Tech	2015		
•	Student Scholarship Grace Hopper Celebration India	2014		
•	Best Technical Poster [S1] Grace Hopper Celebration India	2014		
•	Dean's List Award Bangladesh University of Engineering & Tech	2011-2015		
•	University Merit Scholarship Bangladesh University of Engineering & Tech	2011-2014		
Grants				
•	Postdoc Research Award (sole PI: \$10,000) Title: Designing Accessible Technologies for Collaborative Ideation in Ability-Diverse Tea Paul G. Allen School of Computer Science and Engineering, University of Washington	2022–2023 ms		
•	Graduate Research Grant (\$2,999) School of Communication, Northwestern University	2021–2022		
•	Dissertation Research Grant (\$1,500) Department of Communication Studies, Northwestern University	2021		
•	Conference Travel Grant SIGACCESS Diversity and Inclusion Scholarship for ACM ASSETS conference Northwestern University (~\$6,000) ACM International Conference on Pervasive and Ubiquitous Computing (\$600)	2020 2018–2022 2018		
Teaching Experience				
Northwestern University Dept. of Computer Science / Communication Studies Winter 2022				

Northwestern University | Dept. of Computer Science / Communication Studies Winter 2022 Teaching Assistant | COMP_SCI 314 / COMM_ST 351 - Technology & Human Interaction (56 students)

United International University (UIU), Dhaka, Bangladesh

Oct 2015 - Mar 2017

Lecturer/Instructor | Department of Computer Science and Engineering (CSE)

CSE 313 – Computer Architecture
 Fall 2015: 29 students

- CSE 225 Digital Logic Design
 Fall 2015: 27 students; Summer 2016: 26 students; Fall 2016: 54 students in two classes
- CSE 226 Digital Logic Design Laboratory
 Fall 2015: 77 students in three classes; Spring 2016: 29 students
 Summer 2016: 49 students in two classes; Fall 2016: 40 students in two classes
- CSE 236 Assembly Programming Laboratory
 Spring 2016: 15 students; Summer 2016: 29 students
- CSE 113 Electrical Circuits
 Spring 2016: 67 students in two classes; Summer 2016: 18 students; Fall 2016: 31 students

Course Designed Northwestern University | Accessible Collaboration Mar 2021 Computer Science/Communication Studies undergraduate course | Supervised by Darren Gergle Invited Talks, Panels, and Demonstrations **Talk:** A Design Inquiry into Accessible Crafting within A Community of Blind Weavers Mar 2023 Carnegie Mellon University Human-Computer Interaction Institute | A11y Lunch **Talk:** Designing for Accessible Collaborative Content Creation in Ability-Diverse Teams University of Washington | Makeability Lab Dec 2022 University of Washington | DUB seminar Nov 2022 University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign | Department of Computer Science Apr 2022 Pennsylvania State University | College of Information Sciences & Technology Mar 2022 Virginia Tech | Department of Computer Science Mar 2022 University of Utah | School of Computing Mar 2022 Johns Hopkins University | Department of Computer Science Mar 2022 Indiana University Bloomington | Luddy School of Informatics, Computing, & Engg. Mar 2022 Northeastern University | Khoury College of Computer Sciences Feb 2022 Georgia Institute of Technology | Department of Interactive Computing Feb 2022 Ohio State University | Department of Computer Science & Engineering Feb 2022 Arizona State University | School of Computing & Augmented Intelligence Feb 2022 George Mason University | Department of Computer Science Feb 2022 New Jersey Institute of Technology | Department of Informatics Feb 2022 Massachusetts Institute of Technology CSAIL | Visualization Group Dec 2021 University of Washington | CREATE Oct 2021 **Talk:** Understanding Accessibility in Collaborative Writing for People with Vision Impairments Microsoft Office and Windows Accessibility Teams Feb 2021 Guest Lecture: Understanding Accessibility in Collaborative Writing Input and Interaction Course (INFO 463) | iSchool, University of Washington Nov 2020 Talk: Understanding Accessibility in Remote Work for Neurodivergent Professionals New Future of Work Group | Microsoft Sep 2020

Talk: Designing for Accessible Interaction	
 Bangladesh HCI and ICTD Study and Research Group 	Apr 2020
Demo: Technologies for Accessible Collaborative Writing and Weaving ■ TSB Prospective PhD Students Visiting Weekend Northwestern University	2022, 2019
 Panel: Graduate Life and Research TSB Prospective PhD Students Visiting Weekend Northwestern University 	2021, 2018
Academic Service	
Program Committee Member ACM CHI (Associate Chair, Understanding People: Qual Methods Subcommittee)	2023
ACM Conference on Computers and Accessibility (ASSETS) ACM Conference on Computing and Sustainable Societies (COMPASS) Crase Hopper Colebration, HCL Track	2022, 2023 2021 2021
Grace Hopper Celebration, HCI Track Reviewer: Conferences	2021
ACM CHI [*outstanding review recognitions: 5]	2021 - Present 019 - 2021, 2023 2020, 2022 2022 C) 2021 2017 2016
Reviewer: Journals ACM Transactions of Computer-Human Interaction (TOCHI) Computer Supported Cooperative Work (CSCW), Springer ACM Transactions on Accessible Computing (TACCESS)	2023 2022 2021
Student Volunteer ACM CHI ACM CSCW ACM International Conference on Pervasive and Ubiquitous Computing (UbiComp) InfoSocial Graduate Conference at Northwestern University	2019, 2021 2019 2018 2018
Session Facilitator Human-Computer Interaction Consortium Provocation & Next Steps (breakout ground Asia-Oceania Accessibility Meet and Share Workshop (breakout group)	p) 2021 2021
Publicity Co-chair and Planning Committee Member InfoSocial Graduate Conference at Northwestern University	2019
Outreach & Memberships	
Co-host & Co-organizer Inspiring Stories (podcast series on Bangladeshi women in STEM)	2020 – 2021
Member Association for Computing Machinery (ACM) Special Interest Group on Computer-Human Interaction (SIGCHI)	2017 – Present 2017 – Present
	F

	Special Interest Group on Accessible Computing (SIGACCESS) Northwestern Graduate Women in Computing Bangladeshi Women in Computer Science and Engineering	2017 – Present 2019 – 2021 2015 – 2019
	<i>le Coach Volunteer</i> BraveCamp Chicago, Brave Initiatives (non-profit coding camp for high school girls)	Summer 2018
	e-President Murchhona: BUET (cultural club)	2014 - 2015
Stı	idents Mentored	
•	Aaleyah Lewis PhD student, CSE, University of Washington (UW)	Oct 2022 – Present
•	Ganesh Karthik Sankar MS student, Human-Centered Design & Engg., UW	Dec 2022 – Present
•	Thomas McHugh Undergrad, Learning Sciences, Northwestern University Coauthored paper: [P11]. Own the first place at the ACM Student Research Comp ASSETS 2020 and SRC Grand Finals 2021. Next position: Software engineer, Appl	, ,
•	Evan Li MS student, Mechanical Engineering, Northwestern University	2020
•	Rawan Mohamed Undergrad, CS, Northwestern University	2020
•	Caroline Brewley High school student researcher	2019
•	Nusrat Jahan Mazumder Undergrad, CSE, Bangladesh U of Engg. & Tech Coauthored papers: [P1, P3]. Next position: PhD student, University of Virginia.	2017–2018
•	Khandaker Ashrafi Akbar Undergrad, CSE, Bangladesh U of Engg. & Tech Coauthored papers: [P1, P3]. Next position: PhD student, University of Texas at Da	2017–2018 allas.
•	Fatema Khan Undergrad, CSE, United International University Coauthored papers: [S1, S4]. Next position: Lecturer, Prime Asia University, Bangla	2016 adesh.
•	Ahiya Ahammed Undergrad, CSE, United International University Coauthored paper: [S4] Next position: PhD student, University of Debrecen, Hun	2016